hello whilst recently on my holidays I
met a strange man and he told me I had
two minutes to create a maze that would
take him longer than one minute to solve
so I did this and said solve that there
you go and if you haven't guessed
already this video is about mazes but
more specifically it's about algorithms
and this is an algorithm that I have
loved since I was a child I first
encountered it in the BBC micro
magazines where you have to type in the
programs you sell from acres and acres
of soft listing rarely did the programs
actually work but this one always stuck
with me because it's a fantastic
algorithm and it's perfect and it's
complete and we'll look at the details
of it later and I think it's a great
example of programming and computer
science at its absolute best in just in
case you're wondering today I am living
proof that programmers and code is
actually go outside so there we go now
before we get stuck into the code I'm
just going to provide a quick primer for
the uninitiated and that is what is a
stack because this is fundamentally a
stack based algorithm and a stack can
also be known as a LIFO which stands for
last in first out some people may also
call it a Philo it's the same thing and
the idea is I wanted to imagine a box
like this and if we put some data into
this box it sits at the bottom and then
if we put in some more data into the box
it sits on top but we can't access this
data at the bottom anymore we can only
take off the last bit of data that was
put on there's a little bit of
terminology we always push items onto
the stack and we pop items from the
stack and the top of the stack is always
the most recent item that was pushed
onto it now because this is a video
primarily about algorithms I'm not going
to go into the implementation of the
stack there are many ways to do it
suffice it to say that if your system or
your code uses a stack it will behave
like this now the algorithm I'm going to
talk about for developing a maze is
known as the
cursive back tracker I'm unsure of the
origins of this algorithm but it has
been around for a very long time
and has some fantastic properties but
whenever you want to write code that
involves a more complex algorithm than
normal it's always good to get the pen
and paper out first make sure you
understand it so I'm going to go through
it by hand here on this very simple maze
and it's four by four and along the top
here along my x-axis I've got four cells
0 1 2 3 and I've got my y-axis going
down my plan is to fill this 4x4 array
with maze and I'm going to start by
arming my stack with some data and I'm
going to armed it with the starting
coordinate which in this case is going
to be 0 0 so that's 0 along and 0 down
I'm going to mark that cell as being
visited so any cells that have a blue
blob in the middle are going to be
visited and I'm going to get a tick here
and I'll know when to stop my algorithm
because I should have visited all of the
cells at the end and out therefore I'll
have 16 ticks now I'm not going to make
you sit through all of this I will speed
up parts of it but it's a nice visual
example of how the algorithm is put
together don't forget that even though
there's only one item in my stack the
top of my stack is 0 0 and the algorithm
goes like this from my current position
which is the top of the stack I've got
to choose one of my neighbors randomly
so from position 0 0 here I've got a
choice of this neighbor 1 0 or this
neighbor 0 1 I roll the dice create a
random number and I select 0 1 so I set
that self to be visited and I create a
link update my visited count and I've
pushed the new location on to the top of
my stack so now I repeat I look at my
immediate neighbors and choose one of
them at randomly that I've not already
visited so my immediate neighbors
consists of 0 0 1 1 and 0 2 well 0 0
doesn't count because I've already
visited it after rolling my dice I've
decided that I'm going to move east and
I create a link to it push the new cell
onto the top of my stack that the cell
is visited so one more time with
commentary for completeness I take the
top of my stack I choose a random
direct neighbour so in this case I've
got 1 0 2 1 0 1 and 1 2 I can't use this
neighbor because I've already visited
randomly choosing I'm going to go again
to the east push the new coordinates to
the top of my stack and update my
visited count
so now I've let the algorithm run for a
few iterations and we've hit a problem I
now need to choose a neighbor has not
been visited before so my immediate
neighbors are of course now 0 0 1 1 & 2
0 however they've all been visited so I
have no neighbors which haven't been
visited I've now got to backtrack and
this is where the stack became useful
the stack contains a history of all the
locations that I visited to the top of
my stack is my current location and if I
pop the top of the stack I can move back
one but note I don't remove anything
from the visited column and here I face
the same situation all of my neighbors I
visited before so I've got to move back
one by popping off the top of the stack
now I'm back at this location this is
the first cell as we're backtracking
that's got a neighbor that I can
actually plot into which in this case is
three to all of the other neighbors are
not available they've already been
visited so I've got little choice I've
got to go here this is a new cell so it
becomes visited and we pop the location
onto the stack and now we'll let the
algorithm continue again
but now if it's a dead end again as we
can see
got no neighbors which I've not
previously visited so I've got to
backtrack and I do that by popping the
top off the stack and using the top of
the stack to set my current position
and when I go to this location I do have
one neighbor I have not already visited
and it's the only one I can choose
and so here I've now got sixteen ticks
which is the number of cells that I've
visited this algorithm is really nice
because it guarantees completeness it
doesn't matter how big my maze is it
will fill all of the cell and it
guarantees that every cell can touch
every other cell so it doesn't matter
where you start in the maze you're
guaranteed to get to the objective
location within the maze and like all
perfect algorithms it's completely
scalable not just in terms of dimensions
of the maze but in how you apply it in
this case I've got a single cell where I
can visit my immediate neighbors north
south east and west but it needn't be
the case I could have many neighbors and
apply the same algorithm and get a
perfectly complete maze out of it once
you've visited all the cells it's up to
your rendering algorithm to then try and
draw the maze so in this case I'm going
to fill in wherever I haven't got a link
between two cells so I'm going to draw a
line here and here and here
and once I filled in all the lines
just develops the walls for my maze at
which point we no longer need the stack
and we can get rid of all of this
construction data which leaves us with a
really nice albeit rather small maze
like structure now let's see how we will
do this in code I'm going to start with
a blank int main program as I always do
and I'm going to pull in the one lone
coda console game engine which you can
see in the video marked in the little
tab above now since this is the first
video I've done that uses the technology
I'm only going to go over it very
briefly because you can look at that
other video for the finer details but
ultimately I need to derive a class from
my console game engine which just
handles all of the console stuff for me
if you've seen my other videos you'll
know that all of my programs involve
creating a screen buffer and using get a
sink key state to emulate some sort of
game engine I've wrapped that up into a
nice tidy package that I've called the
one lone coda console game engine and
there are two functions in this on user
create which is where we do all of our
definitions and creating of resources
and on user update which is basically a
per frame function so this is where we
put all the fun stuff and implementing
the class couldn't be simpler we just
create the variable we construct the
console to the dimensions that we want
so in this case it's 160 characters
across by 100 wide and each console
character is going to be 8 by 8 pixels
so then we call the start function this
is only for Windows the construct
console function calls things to the
windows operating system that define how
the console should look but you
shouldn't let that put you off if you're
a Linux or a Mac user the algorithm is
still going to be platform independent
now from my maze algorithm I know that
it's fundamentally stack based so I'm
going to include the stack from the
standard library and in the game class
I'm going to create some variables that
define the maze specifically my maze has
a width a height and I'm going to create
an array here dynamically which stores a
value for all the cells and I'm going to
use this value to tell me which
neighbors the cell is connected to and
so to make this a little bit more
readable I'm going to create an
enumeration here where I'm defining some
constants so for any given cell I can
tell whether it's connected to its
neighbors because
the int value that represents that cell
will contain the bits set in the
appropriate locations and if I visited
the cell as well I know that the
algorithm also requires me to keep track
of how many cells I've already visited
and finally of course I'm going to need
the stack and this might use something a
bit new to the one-line code of videos
I'm using the pair type pair allows you
to store two things at the same time I
could create a struct here myself that
stores an x and a y-coordinate but I'm
going to use the pair anyway why not
this is new and so I have a stack that
stores an object which I've typed pair
but the pair is that templated to store
two integers the first one will be the
x-coordinate and the second one will be
the y-coordinate now I'm ready to
specify some parameters that define my
maze so I'm going to set the width of
the maze to 40 and the height to 25
I've already predetermined that this
dimension looks quite nice on the screen
and because I might want to play with
these numbers later I'm going to
allocate the maze memory dynamically
based on the dimensions we've just set
it's also quite important that we set
all of the elements in the maze array to
0 to begin with I'm using the mem set
command for this and now I need to
specify the staffing conditions for my
maze the stack has to have something in
it to begin with so I'm going to push on
to that a new pair and I'm going to
usually make pair function and we're
going to start like I did when I was
drawing it by hand in the top left hand
corner which means I also have to set
that cell to be visited and conveniently
the top left corner of my maze array
also happens have the index 0 I'm going
to use one of the bits that I set before
and because I've already visited one
cell I'm going to set my visited cell
count to 1 as you can see there's very
little required to initialize this
algorithm but it's important that you do
before we get stuck in with the
algorithm I think it's quite important
that we have a way to visualize it that
way we know if we're coding it in the
right direction so to begin with on the
on user update function I'm going to
clear the screen and that involves
basically drawing a space to my console
in all locations
screen width and screen height from the
top left corner and as discussed
previously my maze consists of a 2d
array of cells so I'm going to iterate
through each of the cells mates with and
mate height and for each cell in the
array I'm going to check does the
integer have the cell visited bit set in
which case if it does we draw a white
pixel or a white block character to that
location on the console or we draw a
blue one so let's just have a quick look
what that looks like well it's a blue
rectangle with a tiny little white dot
so that's good I mean that indicates
that our maze of the dimensions 40 by 25
does have 40 blue characters by 25 blue
characters and the one cell we've
already set to visited in the top left
has been set however everything looks a
bit small and there's a problem we don't
have anywhere to draw the walls I'm
going to introduce the notion of a path
width which will specify how many
on-screen console character cells
represent a single cell in my maze so
for example if the width is set to 2 i
actually occupy a 2 by 2 block of cells
on the console which represents one cell
in my maze then i can surround the two
sides to the east and the south of that
one cell with blocks that represent wall
so here's my 2 by 2 cell and here is a 2
by 2 cell and here is a 2 by 2 cell and
we've now got positioned to add walls I
only need to concern myself with walls
at the east and south side of the cells
because if two cells are linked then
this cell loses its western wall and
this cell loses Eastern wall
ie the wall is shared between them and
of course the same applies for north and
south
so this is now cell position zero zero
and this would become cell one zero and
this one would be 0 1 and 1 1
but the relationship to the console
characters underneath is now the cell
coordinate times 2 to get us to here and
we always plus 1 to give us some wall at
the end and of course that happens in
both axis so we can consider then a
whole complete cell with walls and exits
and everything else is a multiple of
path width plus 1 let's add another
variable to our class path width and
we'll define this as being 3 so our May
cell will represent 3 console characters
across and one for the wall we then need
to modify our drawing algorithm to
accept this change in scale so every
position becomes x path width plus 1
let's take a look well we can now see
that it's spread out across the whole
console which is good but it's not
filled in the individual cells which is
bad therefore I need an additional loop
inside my maze loop here let's draws in
each cell so for each cell in my maze
I'm now going to go through each cell in
the console for the path width and we
just have to add this onto the end
take a look excellent
we now have cells which are 3x3 with a
wall of 1 on our console great we're
also in tourney to draw in our pathways
to overwrite the wall so we can show the
cells are connected so if any of our
cells have the path to East or path to
South set we also want to draw those in
as well and because our walls are always
only one character thick I don't need to
do a two-dimensional plot this time and
get away with a single dimensional one
so I'm just going to go through the path
width one at a time and the first thing
I want to do is check well does the cell
in this case does it have a self path
and if it does I want to draw in the
cells to give us that passageway from
the north cell to the South cell or from
the South cell to the North cell who
knows and we'll do the same for east to
west so if the cell has a passage from
the east to the West in either direction
we want to overwrite the wall the black
cells in the background on the console
we want to draw them in with path color
which is white now we've got a way to
visualize the maze let's get stuck into
the really fun stuff let's actually
create it the maze creation can also go
in the on user update function and we
want to create maze only if the number
of visited cells is less than the width
times the height ie we can only do more
maze development if there are any cells
that we haven't visited step one is to
create a set of the unvisited neighbors
let's consider the North neighbor first
as we're working with 2d arrays we don't
want to go out of bounds and cause all
sorts of memory errors so it's important
that we don't check for neighbors that
the relative bounds of our maze and if
we're checking for northern neighbors
that means we shouldn't be checking for
any if we're currently on the top row of
our mates because they just don't exist
there aren't any northern neighbors so
that's the first thing I'm going to
check for and to do that I'm going to
take our stack and I'm going to look at
the element that's at the top of the
stack using the top function and I'm
going to check because the stack
contains pairs I'm going to check the
second element of that pair which if you
remember is our y coordinate and I'm
going to ensure that it's great
than zero now we're trying to develop a
list of all the neighbors that haven't
been visited so we need to check that in
our maze array and to do this we need to
get the index now we're currently using
the stack and it's using a pair of
second and first for Y and X and so that
looks something like this which you can
see is a bit of a mouthful and we want
to see how's the cell visited flag bit
bin set which will do by checking if
it's equal to one but this isn't very
useful to us at all in fact very
difficult to read and the y coordinate
in this case would get replaced with
minus one because we're checking for the
neighbor above us in our y axis and the
x coordinate gets set to zero because
we're checking in just in vertically
we're not bothered about the east to
west so in the event of us being in a
valid location in the array and that our
neighbor to the north of us exists and
haven't been visited we want to store
this and I'm going to do this by
creating a vector with the vector I'm
going to push to it and identify and in
this case I'm going to use zero that
will say that my northern neighbor
exists and is unvisited and I can use
similar code to check for my eastern
neighbor which in this case I'm going to
use one as the identifier but here I
don't want to check for minus one I want
to check for zero in the y axis and plus
one in the AL are you know what this is
actually getting too much I've just
gotten to the point where I can barely
understand my own code so I'm going to
create a little lambda function to help
me out the lambda function is going to
take an X and a y-coordinate and do this
horrible little bit of offsetting for me
let's change that to an X and change
that to a Y and semicolon and get rid of
this now and just call my lambda
function so if I'm checking in the
northern direction I know I'm not
bothered about X but I'm looking at
minus 1 in the Y that's much much tidier
and I can also do the same for my
Eastern function which in this case I'm
looking along the x-axis by 1 but I'm
not looking in the y-axis at all now you
might be thinking why don't I just do
this with a macro well of course you
could do this with a macro but the
language now provides the auto feature
quite like this I like the lambda
function approach to doing this it means
I'm forced to put the code where it's
needed macros can be any word and a
little bit unregulated they can get a
bit dangerous and fiddly will also
exploit the fact that the if statement
is checked in order so we can get rid of
this secondary call to if which makes
that line of code much more concise now
I'm going to repeat that for the other
directions and here we can see I've got
now an ID of zero for north one for East
two for self and three for West you'll
notice with the east and west neighbors
I'm not using the y component of the
vector to check whether I'm in bounds or
not I'm using the X which is the first
of the pair I've just flagged a little
error here I'm not actually checking if
the cell is visited of course I am
checking if the cell is not visited so I
want to make sure that that is a zero
and not a one my apologies so now I have
a vector that contains only valid
neighbors that I can visit which I might
not have any at all so I need to check
for that if I don't have any then I'm
going to be popping off the stack if you
remember the algorithm before but let's
for now assume that I do have some
neighbors and the nice thing about
bundling things into a vector this way
is it makes other operations easier so I
want to choose a neighbor at random well
to do this all I need to do is randomly
choose a number from the neighbors size
and use that as the index so I can get
something that tells me what direction
is my neighbor now and because I've been
pushing zero one two and three I know
from this identify
which way to go next so that's the value
that gets stored into the next cell
Direction variable the algorithm says
that once I've chosen a neighbor I then
need to create a path between the
neighbor and the cell that I'm currently
in well now that they know both of those
cells I'm just going to use a little
switch block here and fill in the blanks
so let's assume the neighbor is north I
want to create a path to the north so my
current cell which is locally
represented by 0 0 here because remember
this lambda function uses the stack to
work out where they say it always used
at the top of the stack and all of the
coordinates are relative to the location
at the top of the stack so if there's a
path to the north I'm going to or it
with the path to the North bit whilst
I'm here I may as well tell the cell
that's above me ie my northern neighbor
that the one below it has a path to the
south and then going to push to the top
of my stack the northern neighbors
coordinates so as I push to the stack I
create a new pair the x coordinate is
the current top of the stacks x
coordinate plus 0 and the y coordinate
is the current top of the stacks second
part minus 1 so this is the y coordinate
minus 1 to the northern neighbor if any
of this switch block executes it assumes
that I have now entered that new cell so
I need to increase my visited cell count
and I also need to make the cell that I
am currently in so the one that's now
the top of the stack which is the new
cell which I can index with 0 0 now I
need to tell that cell that I have been
visited so I'll just put in new cell
here is a bit of a reminder let's
duplicate this code for the other
options so for South instead of checking
for -1 we're now checking for +1 and of
course the southern neighbor we set the
northern path and we set our current
path to self let's not also forget
the coordinates of the new cell so all
of this was on the condition that we had
some neighbors that we hadn't visited
what if we didn't have any neighbors
well if you remember from the algorithm
before we need to backtrack and because
we're using a stack that's really really
complicated done so let's take a look
and see what happens well I think that's
fantastic we've got a really large and
complex maze and labyrinth okay it's
really nice I'm going to slow down the
algorithm by adding an artificial delay
remember this is just for visualization
it's not that important that we're
breaking some rules here so I'm going to
use the sleep floor function to delay
for 10 milliseconds in each of our on
user update calls this means we'll have
a maximum of 100 cell updates per second
ie were limiting programs through at
about 100 frames per second let's have a
look the algorithm is really pleasant to
watch we can see the choice to draw the
longest path that it possibly can until
it boxes itself in and then it back
tracks to illustrate this I've also got
it to draw the top of the stack with a
green rectangle
in many respects this is similar to a
flood fill algorithm and will probably
definitely have a look at those in the
future and so there you have it the
quick look at a very simple maze
generation algorithm there are many
other algorithms for generating mazes
particularly if you want mazes with a
set of properties such as long corridors
or extra rooms but you can always use
this one as a starting point for example
you could proceed some of the cells as
being already visited now I appreciate
that this video hasn't been as simple as
some of my others and this is going to
happen from time to time sometimes the
topics are quite complicated and need me
to use more advanced coding techniques
than perhaps you see in some of my other
videos and I'm still not sure yet about
using something like the one learned
coder games console engine in the
background I don't know if it does
actually accelerate the development of
the code or the video but I've got some
other ideas for it for other projects
which require things to be a bit more
graphical and I'm trying to avoid
needing to develop a Windows application
anyway as usual the codes going to be
available on github you can download it
hack it generate some mazes for me if
you've enjoyed this give it a thumbs up
it does great wonders for my self-esteem
and please think about subscribing lots
of people have been subscribing recently
and I'm really grateful for some of the
fantastic comments that people have been
leaving so please keep all that up and
I'll see you next time take care