hello it's just too hot to be
programming indoors today so I've come
outside into my garden anyway in this
video we're going to be looking at
something that's become so ubiquitous
you probably don't even realize that
it's there I'm going to be looking at
panning and zooming to demonstrate
panning and zooming I've created a small
application in the COTS or game engine
and it displays a grid at different
spatial scales I can use my middle mouse
button to pick up the grid and move it
around relative to work iver position
the mouse cursor and this is quite
important because it doesn't matter
where I collect the cursor location the
grid moves relative to wordly cursor is
on the screen and this gives the really
compelling effect that I have indeed
picked up the screen space and I'm
moving it around with my hand it's a
very tactile user interface tactic I've
also added the facility to zoom in and
out and we can see here now that the
grid zooms a little bit strangely
because of the very low resolution I'm
using in this application so you see the
cells aren't quite the same size but
that that's irrelevant here what we do
see is that the grid grows and shrinks
but most importantly it depends where
the mouse cursor is as to where the
focus of the zoom point is you can see I
went to the top left there and I'm
moving back out and if I go somewhere
down here in the middle just move the
cursor out so you can see it on the
video and it's always ensures that the
point you're zooming into remains in the
same location this is to avoid the user
getting lost
it also doesn't matter how far zoomed in
we are when we start doing pan
operations the same strategy still
applies and in fact once you have
established a suitable strategy for
world space 2 screen space
transformation we can do everything
through that transformation so I can
even select cells in the grid by
clicking on them and it doesn't really
matter what the spatial scale or
position of the grid is and I can also
move the mouse cursor whilst and zooming
to get a slight rotation effect there so
let's have a quick look at what's going
on and we'll start with the easier one
panning we've actually done panning
several times before in previous videos
for example
the RPG series as the screen panned
around and the Jerry Oh platformer game
series and both of those relied on a
simple concept that we have a screen
space where our top left is zero zero
and we have some world space that
represents the space we want to draw on
the screen I'll just draw that in green
here and the reason I'm drawing it
off-center like this is to make a point
but we can assume that the world space
had a one-to-one relationship with the
screen so top left of the world space
was up here and we also knew that to be
zero zero however to pan this around we
needed to store two offsets one which
was here we're sure it was offset X and
one here offset Y and so if we take a
point somewhere in world space let's say
in this instance it's 10 5 and we wanted
to draw that in the corresponding screen
space which let's say for argument's
sake is about here then the translation
was quite simple we simply subtract the
offsets from world space to screen space
so we go in the X direction and then
again in the Y direction therefore
without any scaling we can get some very
simple equations that the screen space X
location is equal to the world X
location - some offset X and of course
exactly the same goes for the y axis and
we'll see this a lot there's a all these
things happen to both axes
simultaneously and with some very simple
algebra we can work out the
transformation between world space and
screen space so here we've got world x
equals screen x plus the offset simple
stuff we're going to be using these
transformations so much that I really
recommend that we have a world to screen
function and a screen to world function
let's start writing some code to see if
we can
implement panning I'm going to start
with an empty console game engine
project and this time I'm going to
construct a console which is a 160
characters wide by a hundred characters
high and each character is 8 by 8 pixels
so it's reasonably low resolution and in
the on user update function I'm going to
draw a grid but the first thing I'll do
is clear the screen to black if I want
to draw a grid of 10 by 10 cells I need
to draw 11 vertical lines and 11
horizontal lines I'll do this with a for
loop but this for loop you may notice
goes to Y is less than or equal to 10 so
this effectively gives us 11 iterations
through the for loop each cell in my
grid is going to be one unit across by
one unit high and because I want to keep
this code as an example for others to
easily follow and implement in their
application I'm going to be quite
verbose with how I name the variables
and I'm leaving out a lot of
optimizations so for my line I want to
create a start point and an end point
designated by the SX and sy and e ex and
ey values here and typically what I
would do is call the draw line function
to draw a line between these coordinates
however we need to factor in our offset
so we'll come back to this in a little
while somewhere in our system we need to
store the transformation variables so
I'll have two floating point values F
offset X and F offset Y I'll initialize
those to 0 to begin with and now I'll
add my two transformation functions so
this is world 2 screen and a
corresponding screen to world so let's
look at the arguments I'm going to pass
in a coordinate in world space X&Y these
will be floating point but I'm going to
return via the arguments the
corresponding screen space coordinate
and these are integers because our
screen is discretized now we don't have
any scaling at the moment so what I'm
going to do is just handle the panning
so we'll take our screen coordinate and
we'll need to cast that to an integer
because the operation is going to be
performed in floating-point domain and
I'm just going to implement the
equations that we saw before if I can
type
there we go and of course we don't want
to both of these to be ex we won't want
these to be Y in the same way let's
handle the screen to world
transformation this time we'll need to
cast or float our end screen variables
let's go back to where we were drawing
the grid now what we can see is that the
coordinates here are in world space each
one of my cells is one by one I'm going
to need to convert these to screen space
so I'm going to create an additional
four variables which are the screen
space equivalent of the world space
variables and then I'm going to call my
world two screen function now all draw
routines will only occur in screen space
so it's important that we use only the
new variables to do this and I'm going
to draw the line as a solid white line
this code is handled 10 horizontal lines
let's take the same code and repeat it
this isn't optimal we could do
everything in the same loop but I'm
trying to keep it as clear as possible
and we'll use this loop to draw ten
vertical lines as you can see the rest
of the function remains unchanged let's
take a look well we see a rather boring
white square at the top left of our
screen well that's kind of what we
expect because this square is 10 by 10
pixels because us grid was in unitary
cell size remember and our offset is
currently 0 so our world space is a
direct mapping 1 to 1 of our screen
space in on user create I'm going to
default our offset variables to point to
the middle of the screen so I'm going to
take the screen width and screen height
and divide it by 2
but I need to invert this number because
the offset is negative because if we
study our world two screen function
we're going to be subtracting this
negative and adding it let's take a look
now so now we can see that the top left
of our world space is mapped to the
middle of our screen space let's push
the drawing routines to the bottom of
our own user update function and given
this is going to be a heavily
mouse-driven application I'm going to
capture the current mouse coordinates at
the start of the routine
of course the mouse operates in screen
space so whenever the user clicks with
the mouse draw a crude mouse cursor in
here we need world space to be
transformed around where the mouse has
selected because we want world space to
always remain relative to where the
mouse has been pressed and to do this we
need to store some additional offset
information from the top left of our
world space to the current mouse
position in world space so we need to
store this offset too I'm going to call
this start pan X and start pattern Y and
I only want to update these variables
when the user presses the mouse button
so I'll add an if statement that checks
to see has my left mouse button been
pressed if it has it captures the
current screen space mouse coordinates
and stores them in start panics and
start pan Y as the user drags the mouse
we want to update our offset positions
to move the world around so I'll respond
to that on the be held flag as the user
drags the mouse around the screen the
mouse coordinates may change but the
start pan position doesn't therefore we
want to set our offset by the difference
between the mouse coordinates and the
start pan coordinate I also need to now
update my start pan location so in
between frames
it's as if start pan has been clicked
each time I should point out that it
doesn't matter if you're using an
event-driven framework the concept is
exactly the same you just respond to
your on click and on left up and on left
down or appropriate events so let's take
a look now we've got a rectangle in the
screen and it doesn't matter where I
select with the mouse cursor the world
is translated into the screen relative
to my mouse cursor so let's try a really
odd one down here there we go and of
course let's try right in the middle of
the rectangle very nice and we should
also handle something in the negative
domain as well so we know in our world
space the current screen cursor will be
in negative world space and that works
just fine
to put that back in the middle for next
time and that's all there is to panning
it's pretty simple isn't it
however zooming is a little bit more
complicated zooming requires that we
somehow scale the world space as part of
our world to screen and screen to world
transforms so I'm going to store two
additional variables scale X and scale Y
and by default I'm going to set them to
one so that maintains our direct mapping
between world and screen space now to my
shame I have no mechanism for capturing
the mouse wheel as part of the console
game engine I certainly will add that in
the future but typically you would want
to use the pressing of the mouse wheel
as part of the panning operation and the
scrolling of the mouse wheel as part of
the zooming operation I'm going to
emulate this with the Q and a keys being
held down so I want to zoom in
ie make things larger when I hold down
the Q key and all I'm doing here is
increasing the scale value by 0.1
percent and on the contrary if I want to
zoom out ie make things smaller I need
to decrease my scale value also by one
percent different policies for changing
the scale variables can be implemented
here in this instance this is a very
smooth scaling effect you might want to
scale in discrete steps but the downside
to this approach is it is effectively
linear so as you start to zoom in you
need to zoom in a lot more to see any
difference on the screen space but don't
let that put you off trying this method
this gives a very nice feeling zoom now
as I've already mentioned scaling is
simply adding multiplication of the
scaling value somewhere in our transform
and so when we're going from world to
screen once we've transformed the offset
we just want to multiply by our scale
value scale X and F scale Y and if we do
the algebra that means in our screen to
world transform we want to divide by F
scale X here an F scale Y
if you're just starting out on your
programming adventure you always want to
be careful when you see divides like
this because you might hit a divide by
zero error however we've ensured that
that can't happen with the way that
we're handling the zoom value this can
never be zero unless you're one of those
people that would like to start arguing
about the properties of floating-point
numbers so let's take a look here's the
grid and if I press the Q key to zoom in
or we see the grid sort of shoots off to
the bottom right and if i zoom out it
gets smaller enlarges so I'm confident
that the scaling is actually working
but the position of where the scale is
occurring around doesn't seem right and
that's because our scale is completely
centered around zero zero and so the
offset from will to screen space is also
scaled this isn't quite right and we can
demonstrate this to be the case if I
push our world space to be right up in
the top left of our screen space this
will be approximate and I choose to zoom
in we see it zooms in reasonably
appropriately but as soon as I start to
pan it all starts to fall apart it
becomes very difficult for the user to
use instead I want the world space to
scale around where the current mouse
cursor is in world space so here the
black line outlines my screen space and
the green line implements my world space
before I have done a zoom if I want to
zoom around this location so that's
where my mouse cursor is and I choose to
zoom in the effect that I want is that
this point remains the same
unfortunately we already have the
facilities to handle all of this because
if I know where my mouse coordinate is
in world space before I zoom it's here
after the scaling my mouse coordinate
has also been zoomed and if we assume
that scaling is happening around zero
zero which it currently is so my zoom
has actually happened here
so my new mouse
ordinate after the zoom is about here
well if I look at the difference between
the presumed mouse coordinates and the
post zoomed mouse coordinates I can
create a vector which I can use to
offset the new world space because this
vector will be the same as the vector
that we need to displace the world so
before we do any zooming I'm going to
capture the mouse position in world
space and this is very simply done
because we have the screen to world
function after the zoom I want to do the
same thing but don't forget the scale
has changed so the internals of the
screen to world function has also
changed and once I have the before zoom
coordinate and the after zoom coordinate
I can subtract them and update the
offset accordingly to displace the world
around the mouse cursor so let's take a
look well start to zoom in now oh it
seems to be a bit jittery and all over
the place that said it's not going
completely out of control it still
doesn't feel quite right why might this
be well the answer lies here and it's
where we create the offset for the mouse
this currently only ever exists in
screen space we're not doing any scaling
here so I'm going to divide by our scale
values - and you might think well why
was that necessary well if you look at
this this is translating mouse
coordinates differences into a world
space offset and so that's a screen to
world transform slightly different in
this context but we can see in our
screen - world transform we're also
dividing by the scale value - let's try
again hmmm well it's still a bit jittery
but at least now the zooming is actually
happening around the mouse cursor and if
I start to pan the scene that works
equally well - so what's going on with
this horrible jitter and it doesn't take
long for me to discover the problem it's
that I clearly don't know how to program
at all here I'm casting this floating
point calculation to an integer before
multiplying it by our scaling value
I've got brackets in the wrong place I
need to enclose all of this calculation
and now you can see the zoom is very
smooth indeed Schoolboy area though
never mind
well that was all quite embarrassing but
whenever you see sort of jittering like
this that's usually a solid indication
that there is an integer to float or the
other way around conversion not
happening quite as you'd expect it to
now that we have working panning and
zooming
we can start to do other operations
using our will to screen and screen to
world transforms so the first one might
be to actually select something in world
space I'm going to add the two variables
selected cell X and selected cell Y and
at that location in world space I'm
going to draw a red circle so after I've
drawn the grid I'm going to transform
the selected cell in world space to
screen space don't forget my cells were
one by one so if I want the circle to
appear in the middle of the grid I have
to add point five to it in this instance
I also need to scale the radius of the
circle and I'm just going to use the X
scaling factor to do this throughout
this program we've kept scale X and
scale Y independent and this would allow
later on to scale independently in those
axes if you've got a plotting program
for example that might be quite a useful
thing but in this case I know that my
scale X and scale y always change as a
pair so I can take one of them they
always assume the same value and now
that I have my transformed circle
coordinates I can simply draw a circle
in screen space to work out which cell
the user has selected I need to take my
mouse coordinate and translate it to
world space now I already have grabbing
the mouse coordinates is the first thing
that I do in my program and I could
probably get away with using that but
the most accurate Mouse coordinate is
now the mouse coordinate after any
zooming has occurred and so I'm going to
set my selected cell coordinate based on
my transformed mouse world coordinate
after any zooming has occurred I'm going
to do this on a right-click let's take a
look
so I'll just zoom in a little bit here
and we can see in the top left we have a
circle crudely drawn again low
resolution in the cell zero zero and if
I right-click somewhere else on the grid
we can see it's working quite nicely and
of course I can pick it up and pan it
and still select and it selects the
right cells it doesn't matter what the
zoom level is either the transformation
is fine you can imagine this having lots
of applications in level editors image
editors and I think all sorts of
different 2d applications that's why
this is such a useful tool to have in
your programming toolbox there are also
a number of other optimizations we can
exploit now now that we have a mapping
between world space and screen space why
draw parts of the world that you can't
see how can we clip it well I could very
simply create four variables which
represent the left top right and bottom
of the world in screen space and I use
the screen to world function to take my
top left coordinates and put them in
world space and I can do the same for
the bottom right by using the size of
the console and I can use these values
to decide what I draw to the screen or
not I mean after all why draw things
that you can't see so to demonstrate
this I'm going to keep a track of how
many lines that I'm drawing with the
lines drawn variable if a line gets
drawn I'm going to increment that
variable and what we do for white will
also do for X and because we've chosen a
low resolution means I can easily draw
strings and we can read them at the same
time let's take a look so currently all
the lines of the grid are drawn that's
all 22 of them as we start to zoom in we
can see our lines drawn count is
starting to decrease significantly let's
get it down to just the one there we go
so we can optimize our rendering
framework very nicely in fact you could
take this further at the moment it's
still testing all of the lines that's
not necessary either why not only start
drawing from a location which you know
can be seen
you don't even need to do the tests at
all then and finally and very much just
for show enough I'll let you study this
on your own time we can also plot a
graph so let's make a lambda function
which always returns the sine f function
the reason I'm doing this is we can
easily change the nature of this
function and explore it in different
ways now this looks a little complicated
but I'll try and explain what's going on
I'm going to scroll across my entire
screen so I'm looking for all of the
visible pixels from left to right in
world space and in order to do that I
need to know what my world space per
screen pixel
is because I don't want to draw things
unnecessarily but I want to draw things
at high resolution as we zoom in so
calculating this screen width per pixel
is not that difficult I just take the
world right and world left values that I
calculated earlier and divide it by the
screen width that tells me how much
world space is attributed to each pixel
I'm going to store four integer
coordinates which are my pixels to be
drawn which is the current pixel and the
previous pixel because I don't want gaps
in my function either I wanted to draw a
line between successive values and this
line here is just the very first value
to draw so it doesn't draw from zero
zero each time on the function it draws
on the first visible valid location
along the x axis on the screen so I'm
going to loop from the left hand side of
the screen in world space to the right
hand side of the screen in world space
that's my x axis and for each valid
location I'm going to calculate the
function in this case it's up here in
this lambda function it's sign and I'm
going to offset it accordingly in world
space so my grid is effectively ten by
ten I want to locate it to the middle of
the grid and don't forget when we're
rendering on a computer screen positive
Y tends to be going down the screen this
is contradictory to mathematics as we
know it so I'm going to throw in a minus
sign so the sine function is the right
way up for each world space pixel I'm
going to calculate the screen space
equivalent and I'm going to draw a line
so let's take a look and we can see here
we've got something that looks crudely
like a sine wave but I need
to zoom in but it draws from the left to
the right of the screen at all times the
nice thing is it doesn't draw beyond
those locations and I can zoom in and
zoom in and zoom in and the function
never loses any accuracy and I can also
pan so a little bit of a rush at the end
there but it shows you just how
sophisticated having these very simple
transforms can be and so that's that a
very simple yet powerful programming
tool to add to your programmers toolbox
if you've enjoyed this video give me a
big thumbs up have a think about
subscribing all of this source code is
available on github to download and play
with you should come along to the
discord server and have a chat growing
everyday and take care I'll see you next
time