hello this week I created artificial
life but the command prompt of course
just look at how complicated and
sophisticated this life is I've got
clusters of individuals forming families
and groups fighting for resources and
competing for space they're breeding and
multiplying and occasionally you'll see
them sending out a member of the family
to go and interact with other clusters I
am of course talking about the British
mathematician John Conway's Game of Life
which is a class of cellular automata
now you might think that a really
complicated behavior like this would
take several thousands of lines of code
to implement in fact it doesn't it takes
about three and this is why cellular
automata are really cool you can take a
very simple rule set spread it across a
hugely parallel processing substrate and
the resulting emergent behavior can
exhibit all sorts of really complicated
phenomena like several of my other
videos this video we'll use the OLC
console game engine and you can click
the little link above to see more
details about that but essentially all
it does is wrap up the command prompt in
a display buffer so I can draw to it
easily to use the console game engine
you need to create a class that inherits
from it and overwrite two methods which
are on user create and on user update
I've called this class the game of life
and in our in main function now all we
need to do is create an instance of the
class the game of life class and tell it
what dimensions of the console we want
so to start with I'm going to use 160
characters across by 100 down and each
character is going to be 8 by 8 pixels I
then call the start function which will
then repeatedly call the unused update
function this algorithm holds a
particularly special place in my heart
as long as there have been computers
there were people programming John
Conway's Game of Life for them now for a
number of years I worked in academia and
I worked in a field where we developed a
technology called cellular processor
arrays
these are highly parallel processing
devices and to test them we would always
run game of life because if we saw that
it could run life it could probably do
all the other complicated things we
needed them to do I'm not going to go
into the history of game of life there's
an excellent Wikipedia article that will
do just that
and we'll be using this article as a
source of inspiration to try out
different patterns the sheer amount of
research
again flight is vast mathematicians love
it computer scientists love it and
people have proven that it's got all
sorts of fantastic properties for
example it's quite possible to set up a
pattern where the little critters will
move around and implement a fully
functional computer the marula patterns
which can emulate circuits and people
are using it for generating music and
all sorts of interesting sequences but
fundamentally the whole phenomena stems
from very simple rules and I mean very
simple rules and this is why it's such
an interesting algorithm how do you get
all this complex we call it emergent
behavior after such a simple rule set so
how do we make cellular automata well
the first thing you're going to need is
a grid and in this case I'm using a
2-dimensional grid of squares where a
cell is directly connected to its
immediate neighbors every cell in the
grid executes the program and all of
these programs are identical but they
operate on local data each cell contains
a memory which can be used to store its
current state and for game of life this
is very simple it's simply on or off but
it could be much more complicated each
cell has the ability to interact on
communicate with its neighbors and
finally but this is the most important
part all of the cells run a program but
they all run the same program and they
all run the same program synchronized
with each other
this gives way to the SIMD paradigm
single instruction multiple data where a
single instruction is broadcast across
the whole processing array but it uses
these local data to operate on
so this SIMD approach coupled with a
neighbor communication
gives rise to cellular automata the
program for game of life is very simple
step one we count our neighbors
so let's assume I am this cell in the
middle here and I have some alive
neighbors and I was going to be
indicated by red dots we can only talk
to the neighbors in our immediate
vicinity so this gives us a 3x3 square
around the active cell and we can count
how many red dots are in this square so
in this case it's three now this is
where we introduce some very simple
rules let's consider the rules when the
cell is alive ie
its output is set to one so it's got
blue dot or it's a red dot II if the
cell is alive and has less than two
neighbors it dies from loneliness if it
has greater than three neighbors it dies
from overcrowding otherwise the cell has
a good number of neighbors and is happy
we'll put a smiley face on and it stays
alive now let's consider a dead cell
it's not outputting anything but in the
weird world of John Conway if a cell has
three neighbors and it's dead those
three neighbors get together and produce
a living cell and so in this instance
this cell now becomes active in fact so
does this one because it - also has
three active neighbors and that's it
that really is how simple the rule set
is but there is one more important thing
to do we have to do everything at the
same time we cannot scroll through the
cells one by one and update them as
necessary instead we have to treat all
of the cells as if they're in one Epoque
of time as we carry on scrolling through
the cells we can't count the ones that
have already been set on this epoch or
else this one would also become alive
and then this one would also become
alive and these are incorrect results
having seen how simple the rule set is
it's time to do this in code and I'm
going to do this by creating two two
dimensional arrays one that represents
the output and one that represents the
current state of the cell so the output
is what basically we'll see on the
screen and the state is the current
memory within the cell in the unused
create function I'm going to now
allocate the memory for my two two
dimensional arrays and I'm going to
use the screen width and screen height
so that's the 160 by the 100 characters
that we set before and this means I can
choose a console of any size and life
should function appropriately just for
good practice I'm then going to set both
of these arrays to zeros now I'm working
with 2d arrays it's often easier to work
with two-dimensional coordinates so I'm
going to create a little lambda function
here to make it a little bit easier for
me to access the array and in this case
I want this lambda function to return
the value of the output array depending
on my x and y coordinates I'm using the
screen width here to multiply by the way
I'm going to treat the on user update
function as if it's a single epoch so
every time this function is called we're
going to do a full update of the entire
array but before we start to modify the
state of the array we need to store it
in the output so now we're free to
interrogate the output and change the
state of the cell I'm going to use two
nested for loops to iterate through all
of the cells and you'll notice I'm
starting them from the coordinates 1 and
I'm going to the screen with minus 1 on
the screen height minus 1 I'm doing this
to avoid reading memory which isn't
there there are actually several
approaches in cellular automata so what
to do with the boundaries in this case
I'm just ignoring it they're going to
remain fixed but some people do actually
prefer to have ongoing periodic so as
the cells activity goes up one side it
appears on the other the first part of
the algorithm said we need to count the
number of cells in our immediate
neighborhood well I can use the cell
lambda function that I created before to
help me with this so it's just the
current coordinate minus one and this is
the northwesterly cell now because the
value is either a zero one I can just
keep adding these and count them as I go
so in this case I'm not moving along in
the x axis I'm going to put a plus zero
in here just to keep it consistent but
I'm still on the row above and I do this
for all of my neighbors so here is the
North West and here is the South East
I then need to behave differently
depending on whether the current cell is
alive or dead and we
do that by just checking the output so
if the current cell is alive it's set to
1 now if I'm alive and I have 2 or 3
neighbors as said before I'll remain
alive I'll carry on being alive however
in any other condition I'll die so here
I've got a little boolean check and I'm
kind of cheating I'm forcing a boolean
to be an integer value in this case so
if I've got two neighbors or three
neighbors I remain alive because that'll
return true anything else will return
false and kill the cell if I'm not alive
then I only become alive if the number
of neighbors is equal to three
since we're iterating through all the
cells in a nested for loop I might as
well take advantage of this opportunity
to draw them and to do this all I'm
going to do is again check whether the
current cell is alive or not and if it
is I'm going to draw a white character
and if it isn't I'm going to draw a
black character and that's it the
highlighted code is all we need to
implement game of life let's run it and
see what happens so you can see the
console is popped up but hang on there's
no life oh dear well that's because we
haven't got any starting cells we
initialize all of our memory to zero to
begin with well we need some cells to
breed to produce a new cell to test if
the algorithm works or not I'm going to
go through each cell and set the state
randomly to zero or one let's try again
perfect there we go we can see life
quite happily living
I'm going to add a little bit of input
handling code here to check whether I'm
holding down the space key because I
only want life to evolve if I'm holding
the key down this allows us to stop it
and analyze it so I hold the space down
and let go and we can see life stops as
people began to study the game of life
they realize that certain patterns
exhibited certain behaviors the
Wikipedia article lists some of these
and I thought it would be fun to try and
study them more closely so instead of
starting with a random state for all of
the cells I'm going to manually set the
state of some of the cells now I could
do this like so where I manually specify
the coordinates of the cells and put
them into the array however this will
make it a bit tedious to enter the
patterns so I'm going to try something a
bit more visual as before I'm going to
create a little lambda function except
this time it's resetting the value of
the cell so again it takes an X and a
y-coordinate it also takes a type string
the contents of this lambda function
will iterate through the string
character by character and if the
character is a hash it specifies a 1 in
that state location otherwise it's a 0
this leaves us now with a much nicer
syntax for specifying starting shapes
where I can visually see what the shape
should look like to start with let's
have a look this is the our pentomino
I don't like the space bar thing now
instead I'm just going to slow the Fed
down with a wait so from that starting
point we can see it grow and we can see
we've got some spinners and some gliders
the gliders are the ones that travel a
great distance let's try something a bit
more interesting the gospel glider gun
this is an example of an automatic
producing something with a more usable
output let's take a look so here we can
see there's some bouncing back and forth
between two starting points but it
continuously emits gliders our little
life-forms have managed to create a
sequence and don't forget this really
complicated behavior is influences with
just two if statements mathematicians
also found out that it's possible to
have patterns which exhibit infinite
growth let's have a look at this one
this one's all implemented in a single
line
I like the symmetry of this one cellular
automata on a sequential machine like my
desktop PC can be quite demanding of the
processor so I'm going to set it back to
just doing a random start and I set it
to release mode and I'm going to double
the resolution of my console but half
the size of the font and just let it run
away cellular automata is an intriguing
field of research and I've only shown
one very simple algorithm out of many
many hundreds it's not just interesting
to mathematicians and computer
scientists people are now searching for
it in biology and there's some evidence
to suggest that cells in the body might
also interact in this way whatever you
might think I think there is a definite
Beauty to the emergent behavior from
such a simple rule set as usual all the
source code is going to be available on
github if you've enjoyed this video give
me a big thumbs up I will think about
subscribing and I'll see you next time