thanks to curiositystream for sponsoring
this video
welcome folks to a coding challenge i
have done one of these in a while i'm
gonna set myself a timer here and i'm
going to attempt to make a slide puzzle
so this is the source image that i'm
going to use i need to chop it up into a
bunch of pieces
allow you to like click to move the
pieces around and see if you could solve
it to put it back together and have
something detect when it's put back
together that it works all right so one
of the things that we need to use that i
need to use for this is the copy
function um because what i want to do
first is just take this image and chop
it up into a bunch of smaller images so
let me call those
uh the pieces and i'll make an array
and then in setup i should figure out
how many columns and rows that i want so
let's just make it it's
right now it's a 400 by 400 so let's
just make it 4x4
and i also i'm going to probably want to
keep track of like the width and height
of each piece
i probably should do this in like an
object-oriented way where there's like
class piece and that's not happening
right now
four let i equal zero i is less than the
number of columns
uh j
is less than zero j less than the number
of rows
w is the width of the canvas divided by
the number of columns h is the height of
the canvas divided by the number of rows
and then
for each one of these i need to make a
new image or the new the image is a
piece of the larger image so i need to
take the source image and copy from it
oh i think i could just use get i'm
really obsessed with the idea of using
copy because hopefully by the time this
video comes out there will be an entire
video all about the copy function in
processing in p5
let's look at the reference
get i believe
it returns an array of rgba values which
is not what i want i want an actual like
image maybe copy is what i want i know
copy will work in the sense that i can
copy from this image onto this image
let's use copy
so this is fine i'm going to use copy
because i know it's going to work and
the first thing i'll do is create a
blank image
that is
the size of one of the pieces
i really want to use the whiteboard just
because i have a whiteboard so the idea
here is i have a source image
and what i first want to do is on my
canvas
i'm going to chop this up one two three
one two three into four by four and i
want to take this section of the image
and place it on the canvas but keep this
as a separate variable like a piece so
that these pieces can be locked to a
part of the original oh i really need i
just need to know i'm going to i got to
do this object-oriented right because
the piece
should know where its home base is as
well as where it currently is so if
they're being shuffled when all the
pieces are in the right place we've won
so what do i need to make a class
a piece class
that has
a current index
like if i number all these zero one two
three four five six seven blah blah blah
blah i wanna keep track of where it
currently is as well as where it's
original spot it's it's home bases so we
know when the puzzle's solved all right
let's let's do that it's worth it it'll
be worth it so let me uh i got to open
this up here i'm going to make a new
javascript file and i'm going to call it
piece.js
tile it's probably tile is what they are
right let's call it uh tile dot js
so i have a tile class
what does it have in it it has
the index
so i'm going to pass that in as an
argument and
it has its image
so i mean there's probably more to do
with this but i'm basically just want to
wrap the idea of the image's piece and
where it's supposed to be in to this
constructor okay good here we go so now
what i'm actually doing is i'm still
creating the image
then i'm saying copy
uh
what am i copying i'm copying from the
source
zero zero oh no no no no no
the in the source the x location is i
times the width the y location is j
times
h
and i'm copying from the source
i j
with height
two
zero zero with height so if this is
confusing to you
thank goodness i have a white board each
one of these
pieces is an image where this is zero
zero and its height is with an h but if
i'm copying this one
and it's
[Music]
column two
row one boy this is like so messy this
whiteboard but that's fine um then
basically i need to know what is this
location this location is column times
width
row times height and then so take this
section and copy it to this part of the
piece
and i think this is right right it's um
it should be the source image source x
source y source to the destination i
want to copy the source image at this
location
to this destination which is image at
this location great then i need to make
a
a tile is a new tile
index and then the image now what is the
index
the index
is the uh i'm not going to use any
two-dimensional arrays here i'm just
going to keep track of um the the the
individual index counting zero one two
three four five six seven eight nine ten
eleven twelve thirteen fourteen fifteen
zero 15 16 total tiles so the index
is i
plus j times the number of columns oh
let's call this tiles
let's just put all the tiles into an
array
just out of curiosity now
let me loop through that array
and
okay i have an idea let's make a
variable called board
so this is the board the board is an
array of all of the elements in the
order that they're in so board
push index
so basically i'm going to have an array
that keeps track of the positions of all
of the tiles
and then
this is a little bit silly but i'm going
to do it this way i'm going to just
always use a nested loop just to get
that index
and then i'm going to say board
index show so let me just do uh
let me think about this for a second let
me be a little bit more thoughtful here
i'm i was trying to avoid using a
two-dimensional array
but maybe that's silly so i want to have
this array
which i'm going to call board and it's
going to have like it'll be
all of the numbers shuffled in random
order so as i go through
i yes i draw the image
at that spot
like the zero spot what the zero spot
would be x and y but i go look up
image
three or index three from my uh array of
all the tiles i don't know if that made
sense but i had to walk over to the
whiteboard to sort of think through that
in other words x is this is exactly what
i'm doing
x is i times w
y is j times h
and then the image i want to draw is
board
index
it's actually like tiles board
index i mean this is like a crazy way to
write it but i basically want the number
the index that's in the array called
board to tell me which tile to look up
so this is tile i'll call it like tile
index or
right now they'll be in order because i
haven't shuffled it right i'm putting
them all in order and then i should be
able to say image image
x comma y so i'm hoping that when i run
this sketch i'm going to identically see
the image because the only things that
i've done is chop it up into a bunch of
tiles put them into an array in order
and then i'm going and getting them one
at a time and showing them
all right what happened uh oh oh am i
supposed to do create image yeah so i
think i did the dom image element by
accident
tile is not defined oh so no problem
no problem yep
tile.js that's a file i'm working with
thank you very much
uh
failed to actually draw load pixels
yeah create image load picks maybe i
just need to call load pixels i thought
to do copy i don't need to but i must
and then let's do like image update
pixels
let's try that
signature not supported what is going on
oh look at this i deleted some stuff ah
i when i was like mucking around some
stuff got deleted i need all those
numbers all those numbers and i want to
sort copy it from x comma y
nice
[Applause]
okay
i don't even know if i need all these
load pixels and update pixels
still good
okay everybody
oh image equals tile dot image so i need
to pull the image property out of the
tiles
no okay
let's take out all these like
load pixels and update pixels yeah okay
i didn't need any of the low pixels and
update pixels there's a little bit of a
mystery here i have a feeling here copy
is doing the work for us so
we're good now you might not believe me
now this is actually showing it as
separate tiles now let me let me prove
this by just drawing some lines over it
this is gonna be a slightly awkward way
of doing it
but let me just do stroke weight two no
fill
oh but this is silly if i change this to
like width minus 10 height minus like if
i make the images smaller
right okay i just wanted to show you
that i am actually they are separate
pieces so i i visually it might help i
think to actually just draw
little thin lines over it with the
rectangles
and this is very
silly this extraneous
kind of code that i'm doing but um
i think
this will help
yeah so i just wanted to draw some lines
over it now
now we are really getting somewhere
because in theory if all i do is shuffle
this array right have all of the
elements of the array
in random order
then i should see the image
chopped up and moved around so let's do
that so i'm going to write a function
called shuffle which receives an array
uh and then i'm going to
just say like um a hundred times
pick r1 is array dot rand a random
number
floor a random number between zero and
the length of the array
r2
is floor
a random number between 0 and the length
of the array now in theory i don't want
these two elements to be the same but
i'm doing it a bunch of times i want to
swap i'm just the way i'm going to
shuffle the array is by picking any two
elements and swapping their place
so now
temp
is that arrays r1 value
then
and you know i'm going to need i'm going
to write a swap function because i'm
going to need that i think also when i
move the pieces
so function swap
is
uh swap
index i and j of an array
so temp is index i
and then that arrays
i element
is
the j element and the j element is that
temporary value now you might be
wondering like what what and there's a
way i know there's some like object
deconstruction way i can do a swap and
i'll put it up on the screen if i ever
make this into an edited video but
basically the old-fashioned oh the old
old way that we used to swap our
elements in an array is we take element
one
store it somewhere temporary because we
need to put a new thing in that spot and
then we saved it temporarily we could
put that thing we saved in the spot that
just the other thing came out of so now
i want to swap
r1r2
in that array
so let's shuffle
i don't need to shuffle the tiles the
tiles is just an array of elements i'm
shuffling the array that's keeping track
of the index indices of all of them
maybe i didn't need these two arrays but
it's the way that i'm thinking of it
right now shuffle the board
oh
well good thing i wrote my own shuffle
function p5 the reason i'm getting that
error is there already is a global
function in p5 called shuffle and it
uses this fischer yates shuffle
algorithm which i can only assume is
better than whatever i did although is
it the same i don't know we could read
this page and discover we should it
could be another coding challenge the
fischer yates shuffle algorithm you know
what i'm gonna do i'm just gonna call
this a simple shuffle
that way and i could use the p51 you
should try it yourself
there we go look
i have mixed up the elements
all right so one thing that for it to be
a slide puzzle that i need to do
is
i need
to be able to
remove one of them
so
uh columns and then uh let's just
delete the last one pop is it pop
and
that'll be empty
okay great so as long as if tile index
is greater than zero
draw the image
so now
whoops greater than negative one
okay so now i have made the board i
could shuffle it
i could still shuffle it now but this
shuffling is no good
because in theory now is it possible
that it's unsolvable i need a move
basically i need a function that like
moves
one element
so
function
move
so the function is going to receive a
given index
so the idea is i'm clicking on an index
like i'm going to click on one of them
and it's only a valid move if it's above
below to the right or to the left
so i do need this function like the
column is index well you know what i
could
i could pick a random
column or row i need to know where the
negative one is
so let's let's just have a variable
blank spot is
you know what i'm going to do i'm going
to write a function
find blank
so this is a way to quickly check all of
it to find which one is blank
so the blank
i the blank column is the blank spot
modulus the number of columns and the
blank row is
floor
the blank index divided by the number of
rows that's the inverse of putting it
back i should just use the
two-dimensional array
okay so
that's the blank column in row so i and
j if i and j is a neighbor if is
neighbor
i j
blank
there's got to be an easier way to check
if it's a neighbor right
so if it's a neighbor
then swap
blank
with
i plus j
j times columns of that array
so the move
basically the idea of doing a move is
uh there's a spot that i want to move if
it's a proper neighbor to the blank spot
then it can be swapped with it
oh no that's not yeah yeah when you move
a thing and tile into it it becomes the
blank spot okay
so i just need now an is neighbor
function
you the viewer will write this in a so
much better way i'm on a time crunch
here i'm way over my 30 minute limit
function is neighbor i'm just doing x1
y1 x2 y2
well let me do i j
i j x y
so first
if
i is not equal to x
and j is not equal to y
return
return false
it's either got to be in the same column
or the same row so if they're both not
the same
then it's not a neighbor if
the absolute value of i minus x
equals
one
it's one spot away
or
the absolute value of
j minus y
if it's one spot away
returned true and i know i could return
like the result or whatever
otherwise it's the same spot so i'm just
gonna say return false
if it gets the end i think this will
work
just did that kind of like awkwardly
right it's got to both be
in either the same column or row and one
spot away so now
shuffling is should be
picking a move
random
columns
and random rows
i know i could just pick from valid
neighbors to do a move but if i do it
enough times i'll pick valid neighbors
enough times that this should work so
now i should just say move
r1 and r2
and
move if it's a
finds the blank spot and if the blank
spot is a neighbor it swaps it with i
don't know if this is going to work
let's just try it
array ah move
i guess move should the function should
get the array i mean i'm only using one
array
so it's a little bit silly
there we go okay
so that that's a valid shuffling now i'm
just curious let me make this a random
move function
again i will refactor this later i mean
i don't know if i will
let's do random move
so like if i do a thousand moves
oh uh array
it's a little bit silly how i have to
like i'm not using global variables as
well okay so that should be a random
shuffling that's possible but just out
of curiosity
in draw
if i just said
random move
of the tiles but i don't want to shuffle
it i just want to see it doing one move
per
okay cannot read properties of undefined
image
oh board it's the board
there we go oh
oh i'm not drawing the background so the
old piece is there
okay this is it shuffling the puzzle
randomly
oh i love this
all i need to do now is have a mouse
pressed function
i'm going to go back to shuffling it to
start so take out this
and mousepress function is so the column
that i'm clicking on is
floor mousex divided by the number of
columns
right
and the row and i'm gonna call this i
and the row that i'm clicking on
is floor mouse y
divided by the number of rows and then
move i
j tiles
now i'm not giving myself any feedback
or i'm not seeing an animation all of
those are things that i hope that you
will add it should move if it's a valid
neighbor what what did i
so console log i
j
60 oh whoops
no no no no divided by w and h
not divided by the number of columns
divided by the width of the column is it
zero one or two okay
it's like what am i losing my mind here
okay
no oh not the tiles not the tiles the
board the board
yeah look at that
now i'm pressing the buttons and so now
it is solved
if is solved
uh if so console.log
solved
we will not have any fanfare just a
console log solved so i'm gonna write a
function
is solved
where i'm going to go 4 let i equal 0 i
is less than board dot length
minus 1. i don't need to check the last
one
i plus plus
and then if
board
index i is not equal to
tiles index i dot index right isn't that
didn't i save where it's supposed to be
yes in the tile class
then that's a piece that's in the wrong
place
so return false
and if you get through everything
all of them are in the right place
return true so if i don't shuffle
the board at all
it's solved it's showing me it's solved
now if i shuffle it in setup
it's not solved and i can solve it okay
let's make it easier for me to solve oh
my god i think i got this i think i did
it
so let's just shuffle it
simple shuffle like
five times
okay no it didn't pick oh there we go
okay great so in theory all i need to do
is just click on this element
it will move up and go into place
solved
yay okay awesome so um just for fun
cause what are we doing but having fun i
am going to
have it be eight by eight
and i am going to let it shuffle a
hundred times
like i guess there's more pieces it's
not going to pick the thing randomly but
hold on this is a little bit harder
solved i did it
no let's keep it but this is kind of fun
because you realize you could do like
you know
a 20 by 20 slide puzzle here
right and how many times do i need like
you know obviously again i need a better
shuffling algorithm but if i do it 10
000 times
you know that's a lot of interesting
moves there but let's go back to making
it four by four and make this puzzle
solvable for myself this is the last
thing i'm going to do
i'm gonna make it four by four
i'm going to shuffle it just 100 times
and let's see if i can solve this
oh shoot
oh wait a sec
[Music]
i think i did it
yes
i solved it all right
so what can you do well you can be more
thoughtful about what image you pick you
could add animations there's a million
opportunities to refactor this code to
make it more s make more sense i mean
this object could do so much i started
like i need to make this object-oriented
but i did not follow through with that
but also one prompt that i would have
for you is there's no reason you
couldn't do this with a video or some
abstract generative art drawing i mean
so many possibilities there because as
long as you have an image even if it's
an image that's changing over time you
can shuffle it and you can solve it and
a move counter for scoring so many
things
if you like this coding challenge video
and are wondering what happened inside
all of those little cuts and edits i'd
like to encourage you to sign up for
nebula and curiosity stream nebula is a
streaming platform for me and other
educational creators where you can watch
ad-free versions of the coding train
videos as well as the 45-ish minute
uncut version of this coding challenge
with all that extra debugging time
you'll also find ad-free videos and
bonus content from a variety of other
great channels like jordan herrod
tierzoo and practical engineering
you'll also get access to nebula
originals that you can't find anywhere
else like better elevation a deep dive
into new tools creators use to
supercharge their productions
the best way to sign up for nebula is
through curiositystream who are kindly
sponsoring this video curiositystream is
a subscription service with thousands of
documentaries and non-fiction videos if
you like the coding train i have a
feeling you are going to love watching
calculating ada the countess of
computing hosted by the amazing dr
hannah fry along with numerous other
films and series about mathematics ai
and computing if you sign up using this
link that's going to magically appear on
screen or the one that's in the video
description promo code coding train you
will get 26 off curiosity streams hd
annual plan as well as access to all of
nebula that's less than 15 for the
entire year not per month the whole year
it's a great way to support the coding
train find ad-free and some uncut
versions of my videos as well as
discover lots of other wonderful
creators sign up with this link or on
curiosity stream's website with the
promo code codingtrain thank you for
watching this coding challenge and i
will see you next time on the coding
train
[Music]
you