hello this week we're going to start
taking a look at splines and how you as
a coder can use them to enrich your
applications and games in short splines
are a way of algorithmically
representing a curve and even though you
might not think you need curves in your
application you'll be surprised just how
useful they can be for example if you're
making a game why do your game objects
need to move in straight lines they can
look a lot more fluid and natural if
they follow a curvature what if you're
interpolating between two points again
don't use a straight line use a spline
you've probably already encountered
splines and don't really realize it so
here in humble paint this is a spline
and we can position the curvature and
you probably experienced the frustration
of trying to curve it just how you
wanted it always seems to have a mind of
its own we see from the paint example
that we'll have two control points and a
third one which is used as an indication
of where the curvature should tend
towards and if we were trying to
represent a longer path using more
points in this fashion we have to pretty
much guess where those control points
need to be
we'll also face issues about what
happens when you try to join two splines
if we have a look at the Wikipedia
article for splines we'll see that it's
actually quite mathematical and this can
make it inaccessible for the one loan
coders out there who just want to get
some curvature into their application
that said the maps behind these things
is quite fantastic and we'll be looking
at some of it when it comes to
programming we rarely like guesswork so
deciding where to put these control
points is not ideal so we'll not use
that type of spline instead the type of
spline I'm going to be explaining in
this video you can use multiple control
points and the path is guaranteed to go
through all of them
and to use this I'm going to use a type
of slime called a cat mole realm spline
and an interesting fact there is the mr.
cat mole in the cat Milgram here is one
of the founders concurrent president of
Pixar so this guy knows his stuff when
it comes to computer graphics in its
most basic form a capital R arm spline
contains four points which are denoted
here with the red blue orange and green
dots justice gathers going with some of
the notation we usually refer to as p0
p1 p2 and p3 a camel runs flying will
only generate a curve between p1 and p2
and it uses p0 + p3 as a guide to what
angle the curve should be going through
the points p1 and p2 to find a point
along the spline we usually use a value
T which begins at zero for point 1 and
ends at 1 4 point 2 so we're accessing
the curve segment in normalized space
and the nice thing about Catmull ROM
splines is the points can be
multi-dimensional so even though it
traditionally would have X&Y we could
have more dimensions afterwards and the
mathematics doesn't change just scales
up so I'm going to try and start
explaining how a spline works without
getting involved with the mathematics
just yet and I find it useful to think
about the points as being the center of
influential circles that guide our point
T so simply put as we approach p2 we're
more influenced by p2 and we become less
influenced by P 1 because we're further
away so of course if the point lies
directly in the middle of p1 and p2 were
equally influenced by both the points
and if the point on the curve are
interested in happens to lie on one of
our control points were 100% influenced
by that control point and nothing comes
from the other control point so what a
points p 0 and P 3/4 then well if we
just had the point P 1 and P 2
influencing the curve we would get a
straight line which you don't need me to
tell you isn't a curve so in a similar
way to the circles of influence from P 1
and P 2 p 0 and P 3 also are influencing
our point on the curve but in a much
more mild way so whereas we saw P 1 and
P 2 attract our target points p 0 and P
3 repel the target point and we can see
in this example that the curve pushes
upwards using the desmos comm graphing
calculator we can have a look at the
maths behind the spline consider the x
axis along the bottom to represent our
variable T in normalized space so it
goes from 0 to 1 and if we remember for
our point that was blue which is a p1 we
want to have a full influence when we're
on the point and we want to have no
influence at all when we're on the other
extreme of the curve in this case p2 so
in this way consider the y-axis to be
the amount of influence the point has on
our point T going around the curve
segment naturally then it follows that
our orange point which was p2 has an
opposite looking curve so it is not
influenced at all by p1 but as we
increase our T point along the curve
segment it becomes fully influenced by
the time it gets to point 2 let's
consider p0 now this one looks a little
strange positive influence in the Y
Direction is attraction ie we bend the
curve towards the point so p0 the red
point here goes negative which pushes
the point away as I showed with the
arrows before and likewise we have a
mirror image curve for p3 the final
point all of these functions are cubics
so this is a cubic spline
if you've ever tried to use the pen tool
in Photoshop you'll know why this is
important at each spline control point
we can specify a gradient but the curve
doesn't necessarily go through the
points this makes this tool incredibly
frustrating to use but it does highlight
one of the limitations of the Catmull
arm spline that we cannot specify the
gradient through a point the gradient is
always calculated by the position of its
neighboring points these equations are
only valid for one component of our
point vector so in 2d space we'd have to
calculate all of these for X and all of
these for y to give us the XY point on
the curve segment I think it's time to
start putting these into practice so
I've created a new console project and
I'm going to use our old friend the OLC
console game engine so we can visualize
the splines as most of my viewers will
know by now the OLC console game engine
just simply wraps up the console in a
way that it repeatedly displays
information to the screen and it also
accepts some user input and we need to
override two functions in this class the
unuse are create and on user update
functions I'm going to create a console
application that's 160 characters wide
by 80 characters high and each character
in the console is going to be 10 by 10
pixels let's start by creating a
structure that represents a 2d point so
I'm just going to have an X and a y
coordinate I'm going to create another
structure now to represent the spline
and the spline is going to consist of a
vector of points let's start by getting
some of the visualization out of the way
in my game engine class I'm going to
need a spline object which I'm going to
call path and in the unusal create
function I'm going to populate that path
with points so these are coordinates of
console characters on the screen and
they represent the control points in the
spline there's only four of them now
let's try to draw these to the screen
first thing I'm going to do is clear the
screen which I'm doing by drawing space
to all characters then I want to iterate
through all of the points and draw them
to do this I'm going to use the fill
function to draw one pixel either side
what one character either side of all of
the control points it's going to use the
solid character and it's going to call
them red this will give me a 3x3 block
to represent a control point and in the
middle of that 3 by 3 block I'm going to
draw the index of that control point so
we can see which ones which
let's take a look perfect I want to move
the control points around the screen so
I'm going to create a variable that
represents a point that's selected for
movement we'll initialize it to 0 so
let's handle a little bit of input from
the user
if the user presses the X key I want to
increment my selected point variable but
I'm also going to make sure that it
doesn't go out to bounce so if it does
it rotates it back round to 0 again I'm
going to do the opposite with the Zed
key which this time decrements the
variable now I want to move the selected
point around depending on the arrow keys
so I'm going to check if an arrow key is
held down in this case left and if it is
I'm going to move the selected point x
position by some value in this case I'm
picking 30 because it will be a fast
movement and if I modulate that with the
elapsed time it'll be smooth depending
on the performance of the system and
likewise I can do the same for the other
arrow keys I think it's important that
we highlight the currently selected
control point so I'm going to use
exactly the same code as I've done here
except instead of coloring it in red I'm
going to color it in yellow and
obviously I'm going to use the selected
point variable instead of the eye in the
loop let's take a look
so we can see the zero control point is
currently highlighted and I can use the
arrow keys to move it around and if I
use the Z and X keys I can move any
control point that I want so how do we
draw the curve I'm going to create a
function called get spline point which
takes in a value T and returns an XY
coordinate for now I'm just going to
hard-code that is zero zero drawing the
spline is a little tricky and I want to
make sure I'm drawing it behind the
control points remember we're using the
curve to generate an XY position based
on a normalize coordinate so we're going
to issue a 0 to a 1 and it will return
an XY for that point on the curve so
let's create a little for loop which
iterates from 0 to 1 and I'm going to
nibble at it in very small steps and
we'll see that this is actually one of
the downsides of using splines for each
value of T I'm going to call our spline
point function which should return the
XY coordinate and I'm just going to draw
a pixel at that XY coordinate but of
course at the moment
it'll only draw something at 0 0 because
we need to fill in I'll get spline point
function we've only been given the value
of T so we need to create some indices
based around that value T we know for
example if T was say not 0.3 then P 1
would be the floor of T which in this
case would be 0 from there we know that
P 2 is P 1 plus 1 we know that P 3 is P
1 plus 2 and we know that p 0 is P 1
take 1 so let's do exactly that I'm just
going to cast to an integer to do our
floor equation and of course because I
code these things live I've immediately
noticed a mistake it's p 0 1 2 3
we can now start to implement our
equations so I know that I'm going to be
using T squared and T cubed a lot so I'm
going to cash these I'm just going to
take the equations exactly as I had them
in the desmos graphing calculator to
give me four values which are
influential field values to calculate
the result we do it one axis of the time
so I'm going to look at the x axis first
we need to take the point that we're
interested in so in this case the first
one is p0 and we're only looking at the
x-coordinates at the moment and we've
multiplied that by our first field of
influence which was the red line the red
point and then take the next point along
and use our second field of influence
and so on
so the four influential fields are
multiplied by their respective point
locations in the x-axis I can cut and
paste this to do the y-axis and just
change the X components to Y components
instead of returning zero zero will
return txt y there is one final thing to
do if we examine these equations we see
that the influence on the y axis lies
between 0 & 2
we want this to be between 0 & 1 so we
will have all of the values
let's take a look well there's certainly
something on the screen let's see if
it's behaving so I'm going to move this
control point down we can see it does
start to repel some of the curve let's
move this control point over a little
bit okay I'll bring this one round too
so we'll make it look like we had in the
diagram before however there's some
reason it's a dashed line why is this
well that's because we nibble through
the zero to the one in a small increment
and if we're only incrementing in naught
point naught 5 that means really we can
only have 20 pixels between the two
control points and if they're 40 pixels
apart we'll skip every other pixel so we
need to make this smaller let's have a
look that's better
that one curve segment on its own isn't
very impressive so let's add a lot more
points
so here I've added a point every 10
pixels in a straight line we've now got
more than one curve segment so we need
to adjust our drawing routine
accordingly now I take the number of
points in our path and I'm going to use
that to calculate Mike T note that I'm
subtracting a value from them I don't
want to draw the two control points at
the end of the spline let's take a look
hmm something doesn't look quite right
here oh dear let's see why this might be
well our T is going to go above 1 so we
need to modify our get spline point
function to accommodate this and this is
quite simple because we've already got
the floor of our tea to give us our
first control point we just want what's
left over
so our control points will represent one
two three and four and any remainder
that comes in is what we're going to use
to index into the normalize point of the
curve segment this looks a little better
let's move some points around very nice
and so you can see with more control
points we can have quite elaborate
curves let's just take a minute to look
at an interesting property of this here
I've laid out the points in what appears
to be a loop and in fact if I take the
two end points which in this case will
be one and eight and overlap them that
would actually make a loop but it's a
loop with a bit of a kink in it around
the point eight but I can get rid of
that by using the two original end
points and overlapping those with the
two neighboring points which gives us a
nice perfectly curved loop and so if we
wanted our splines to be loops we could
just manipulate the indices when we're
trying to calculate our spline point and
therefore we know that our loop goes
through all the control points if we
want our spline to be looped we have to
treat it differently I'm going to modify
our spline point function if it's not
looped we just do what we did before
which will give us a curvy path but the
ends won't join but if it is looped we
can take our T variable calculate the
indices in a similar way to before but
this time wrap the indices around all of
the points in the vector so let's say
I'm approaching the point towards the
end of the vector I can use the modulus
function to wrap it round to the staff
and likewise if I go below zero I can't
use the modulus function for that but I
can do a little trickery here to give me
the point at the other side of the
vector
you should also modify our drawing
function now to go through all of the
points but we must tell our spline
function that it is loops now let's take
a look well it looks like a straight
line again but as I start to move the
points around
we can see they're certainly joined
nice now we have a facility where we
could control an AI character let's say
for example a spaceship to follow a path
around space and it will look very
natural it won't have to move at right
angles or turn at fixed intervals and
the path can be modified in real time so
with a simple bit of mathematics we can
generate a very natural-looking behavior
but what if we wanted our spaceship to
follow the path precisely for example in
this instance our spaceship is only
getting an x and y coordinate will
always point in the same direction
regardless of where it's up to on the
path instead what we would prefer is
that the spaceship carry on pointing in
the direction of the path depending on
where it is and we can do this by
extracting the gradient at any point a
crude way of guessing the gradient at a
point will be to take it to control
points and create a straight line
between them and that would give us an
approximate gradient maybe but a better
way is to modify our spline equations to
give us a precise gradient in a similar
way that we calculate the position
unfortunately this is very simple indeed
if you remember before we were
calculating our Q values which were the
influential field so we have something
like minus T cubed plus 2t squared take
1 all we need to do is differentiate
this equation which becomes minus 3t
squared plus 4t take 1 and we can do
that for all of our equations so I'm
going to take our entire point function
here and duplicate it I'm going to call
this one get spline gradient
and everything else can remain the same
but I'm going to change these equations
I'll just cut and paste the others in
there we go so let's hack something in
to demonstrate that we can extract the
gradient the agents location is going to
be represented by a variable called F
marker so we need to have some keys so
we can increment and decrement this
variable I'm going to use the a and s
keys to change it but I want to make
sure that I keep control of this
variable so I'm also going to put some
boundary checks in so if the marker
value goes larger than the number of
points in the path then it wraps around
like we did before with these E and X
keys I'm going to draw on our path where
the agent currently stands so to do that
I'm going to get the point on the path
this assumes we're looping at the moment
I'm going to get a point on the path
where the marker location is and I'm
also going to call I'll get gradient
function for the same point to draw the
agent I'm going to draw a line which I'm
hoping is going to be orthogonal to the
path at all points so let's have a look
at this the first thing I do is
calculate the angle of the gradient
returned by the get spline gradient
function so this will return an XY
vector but I'm going to convert it to
radians and I'm going to use the draw
line function which is provided by the
game engine to calculate two points that
are rotated around p1 which is where our
agent is on the path by the angle
represented by the gradient I'm going to
offset these by 5 pixels so I'm going
from one point here which you can see is
a plus 5 to a minus 5 and this will
hopefully give me two points either side
of the path I'm going to draw this blue
let's not also forget that we're working
in loop mode here so let's take a look
well I can see the agent is definitely
orthogonal to the path let's make it our
path a little bit more interesting
it's always very satisfying watching the
curves sort of unfold themselves and we
can see the agent starting to rotate
depending on the orientation of the path
so if I use the ANS keys we can see the
agent follows the path now because I'm
incrementing its position along the
curve then it wraps around very nice so
this video is showing you how to create
a path and spline between all the
control points and I think it's quite
useful for things like a non-player
character ai or animations but there is
still a few things to work out so as I
move my agent around we can see is speed
varies and this is because it assumes
that the distance between all of the
points is the same 0 to 1 we'll come up
with a solution for this in part 2 of
the splines video all of the code for
this video is available on github if
you've enjoyed it please give me a big
thumbs up have a think about subscribing
and I'll definitely see you next time
and I'll definitely see you for part 2
of this video so take care